Guide to the Photograph album of Aden Protectorate AD.MC.110
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Photograph album of Aden Protectorate
1932
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
AD.MC.110
0.10 Linear Feet in one album, with 38 photographic images (affixed to 18 pages and inside covers).
Photograph album, containing 38 silver gelatin prints depicting scenes in and around Aden Protectorate, likely taken by an unknown British soldier stationed there in 1932.
Conditions governing access
The Photograph Album of Aden Protectorate is open for use in the Archives and Special Collections Reading Room at New York University Abu Dhabi.
Immediate source of acquisition
This album was acquired by the NYU Abu Dhabi Library in July 2022.
Arrangement
The photographs are described in the order in which they are arranged in the album, with excerpts from the captions included in each description.
Historical note
British Forces Aden, as the British armed forces stationed in Aden Protectorate were known, was originally established as the Aden Command in 1928, and renamed British Forces Aden in 1936.
British forces captured Aden in 1839, seeking a strategic base in southern Arabia that could be used to protect British interests in the region, and in particular trade routes to and from India. Initially, the port of Aden was administered by British authorities in India, but during the course of the 19th century, treaties were drawn with local rulers, leading to the establishment of the Aden Protectorate, an area which encompassed the port of Aden and surrounding territories, and which the British had hoped would serve as a buffer to the Ottoman Empire. In 1937, the protectorate became a Crown Colony of the British Empire. By the 1950s, under pressure from Arab nationalist forces in surrounding countries, the British brokered agreements with local rulers to form the Federation of South Arabia. An insurgency of anti-British guerrillas eventually led to the full withdrawal of British forces in 1967, and the subsequent establishment of the Marxist-led People's Democratic Republic of Yemen.
Source: Wikipedia, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aden_Protectorate, accessed 16 July 2025.
Content Description
Photograph album, containing 38 silver gelatin prints depicting scenes in and around Aden Protectorate, likely taken by an unknown British soldier stationed there in 1932.
Two of the images in the album depict a soldier named Jack, who may have been the creator of the album. Photographs depict various scenes in the city or Aden, but chiefly related to areas where British military forces were present, such as their headquarters and soldiers quarters, but also some of the nearby scenery, such as Elephant Rock and the Crater. The creator of the photographs ventured outside of the city, to Lahij, a town to the north of Aden, as well as a place the photographer identified as "El Khu-dhad," where he photographed locals with their cattle. Also included are photographs of Jack and his friends in leisure pastimes, including fishing and visiting the beach with his dog.
Aden (Yemen); Great Britain -- Armed forces -- Yemen, South
- Images (2): "Jack, August 1932" and "Plantation, up-country Aden." (Volume 1, Page [inside front cover])
- Images (2): "Aden, from mountain top" and "Myself and two mates.", April 1932 (Volume 1, Page 1)
- Images (2): "Two mates of mine" and "I am coming down the mountian" [sic]., April 1932 (Volume 1, Page 2)
- Images (2): "Gibraltar, on the voyage out" and "Tarabyne, entrance to Aden, known as Hell's Gateway", May 1932 (Volume 1, Page 3)
- Images (2): "Headquarters, taken from bungalow, Aden..." and "The road leading to bungalows...", May 1932 (Volume 1, Page 4)
- Images (2): "Barren rocks..." and "Veranda of our bungalows...", May 1932 (Volume 1, Page 5)
- Images (2): "Elephant trunk, Aden" [rock formation] and "Part of sport fields...", May 1932 (Volume 1, Page 6)
- Images (2): "Crater" and "Cement mixer", undated (Volume 1, Page 7)
- Images (2): "The well, La Hedhge" [Lahij] and "Sultan's palace, La Hedhge" [Lahij], May 1932 (Volume 1, Page 8)
- Images (2): "Camel market, La Hedhge" [Lahij] and "La Hedhge [Lahij], city on the edge of the Arabian Desert", May 1932 (Volume 1, Page 9)
- Images (2): "El-Khu-dhad, jungle" and "El Khu-dhad, knocking off time for the cows...", May 1932 (Volume 1, Page 10)
- Images (2): "El Khu-dhad, oh, to be a farmer boy..." and "Jack", May 1932 (Volume 1, Page 11)
- Images (2): "Looking for the boat" and "Fishing", undated (Volume 1, Page 12)
- Images (2): "One big splash" [waves on shore] and "My dog", undated (Volume 1, Page 13)
- Image (1): "The inside of our church", undated (Volume 1, Page 14)
- Image (1): "The sultan's palace, it is all marble", undated (Volume 1, Page 15)
- Images (2): "Steamer point, Aden" and "Football field, game at 115 degrees", 1932 (Volume 1, Page 16)
- Images (2): "A tunnel through the mountains, army storage" and "a snap taken halfway through", undated (Volume 1, Page 17)
- Images (2): "Post office, Aden" and "the Moslem place of prayer", undated (Volume 1, Page 18)
- Images (2): "This ship got burnt-out 300 miles away from Aden" and "Village of El Khe-dhad", May 1932 (Volume 1, Page [inside back cover])